Have you ever seen a feeble elderly
person? Picture them in your mind. They
may get up very slowly, if at all,
unassisted. They shuffle as they walk
instead of taking confident strides.
They simply can't lift up certain
day-to-day objects. That is frailty.
That is age sapping us of ourselves.
Now, think of someone of a comparable
age, maybe in their 70s or 80s or
beyond. Yet, they stand up without fuss.
They move about confidently. They move
simple objects without much issue. The
difference between those two scenarios
is striking. It's overwhelming even. And
one of the keys to that difference is a
tissue that you use all the time. It is
muscle. Even more impressive is that
this tissue is called postmitoic,
meaning that once you're born, the same
muscle cells propelling you in childhood
are the same ones sustaining you 50
years later. That is quite different
from many of the other cells of your
body that divide and die as needed. So,
you can imagine that taking care of them
is pretty critical. And I'll show you
exactly how critical it really is by
leaning on this study right here. Now,
if we compare young whippers snappers in
their 20s against various groups of
older individuals in their 70s, we get
some incredible findings. You ready for
this? Check this out. We have the four
groups shown in the bottom left corner
of each image. Now, if you've never seen
this before, what we're looking at are
cross-sections of muscle tissue. So,
each of these blobs, which have defining
lines around them, is a muscle cell.
You'll obviously notice that some are
blue and others are red, which isn't
natural. We, and I mean researchers,
apply different stains to the muscle
cells to identify the type of muscle
that we're seeing here. So, the stain
identifies if the muscle cell is a type
one or a type two. Now, a bit like a
type A and type B personality. So, type
one labeled in blue tends to produce
less force, but generate force for
longer periods of time. Type two,
labeled in red, tends to produce more
force, but for shorter periods of time.
Now, neither is good or bad. They both
serve a function. But as we age, we tend
to experience a shift to type one as we
lose the force generation ability of our
muscle cells. So that context in mind,
we tend to shift blue with age. What do
you see here? That's right. The old
control do shift blue as predicted and
shown across many studies. However, look
at the other two old conditions compared
to the young. There's certainly more
red, but especially in those that
strength train. But what's unique about
this situation is that these older
individuals have been exercising for
literal decades, their whole lives
practically, just in different ways. So
some focused on endurance training, some
on strength-based training. So
long-distance runners or bikers for
those in the endurance camp and
powerlifting and strength training for
those in the ladder. So the main point
here is that those who have been
strength training for the last 50 years
have a closer muscle type profile to
young muscle. Still, that doesn't tell
us about the actual function or if this
is a consistent truth. Keep in mind I
just showed you a single image, not the
average data collected from many people.
Well, I can tell you that this fiber
type difference is still maintained when
looking at more people. And as for the
functional measures, as in does this
translate into greater strength? The
answer is well, look for yourself.
Again, the higher the bars go, the
better the performance of that group.
So, the old group that did not engage in
exercise on a dedicated regular basis
had the worst results across the board,
likely speaking to the power of aging.
But what can overcome this power? Like
Vegeta turning Super Saiyan for the
first time and ripping Android 19 apart.
Strength training. Not only does
lifelong strength training maintain
muscular performance, but the
participants performed better than those
50 years younger than them. Let that
sink in. This tissue that's been part of
you since you were born that has had to
endure a lifetime of work delivers
another mindblowing performance. To be
clear, the young group weren't sitting
on the couch all day either. They were
recreationally active. Now admittedly
not bodybuilders or powerlifters but
still healthy, young, and active. The
ability for muscle to preserve its youth
is one of the greatest biological
marvels I've ever encountered. The point
here is that strength training
throughout life maintains much of the
youth of our musculature. Not just in
the shape, but more importantly in
function. 50year difference. I mean
that's incredible. The reasons are many
from the stimulation to the actual
muscle cells that leads them to grow to
express genes that maintain the
structure of the muscle cell to
something that happens outside the
muscle called denervation. If you're
interested, I'm going to be getting into
the deervation as well as something
strength training does to our stem cells
as we get older from a different study.
That's all included in the extended
video of the one that you're currently
watching. Exclusive for the Physionic
Insiders. Plus, all these perks right
here, as you've likely heard me mention
many times before, an insider membership
gives you access to all my work,
summaries, podcasts, live sessions,
greater access to the insider community
and me, and much more. The link to join
is in the description. Hope to speak
with you over there. Okay, we clearly
saw significant benefits linked to
lifelong exercise. And I certainly am
not going to turn around and claim that
that is now all nonsense. But I would
like to note two important things. One,
the main study that we've been focused
on is a comparative study. So they're
not actually following people over 50
years of life. They're simply grouping
people based on this exercise
characteristic. In this kind of study,
we can't officially say if it's exercise
alone or exercise in general leading to
these results. For example, the
strength-based older athletes could all
be taking testosterone or have an
incredibly anabolic diet or whatever the
reason. I do think it's unrealistic to
think that exercise didn't play a major,
if not the major role in these
differences, especially considering that
it being a consistent throughine
throughout the decades, unlike other of
these many factors, you know, like
testosterone. So, my belief, though I
can't say for certain, is that exercise
is the primary explanation for what we
saw. Second, not all studies that look
into this agree. most trend in this
direction, but the exact results. For
example, similar, if not better,
strength in mast's athletes is not
universal across studies. That is likely
explained by the different ways that
studies assess the same measure. For
example, in this study, they focused on
leg press, a great and controllable
exercise. However, would these results
remain if we looked at something like, I
don't know, a barbell curl, a pull-up?
You see, the measure is the same, but
how it's measured is different. I'd
suspect that's a major contributor for
some of these differences in results. To
be clear, almost all the studies show
these improvements. It's just the degree
of improvement varies somewhat. So,
what's the takeaway here? Well, we're
playing against time. If you're already
in your 70s, you might think that this
study is pretty useless to you, unless
you've been exercising for decades, in
which case you're literally jumping for
joy. But don't despair. The saying goes,
the best time to do something was
yesterday and the next best is today.
And it's not just a saying. There's
truth to it scientifically speaking, as
I'll direct you later. The takeaway here
is that start exercising early and take
it seriously. Do it consistently. The
second takeaway is to focus on strength
training for the best bang for your buck
in maintaining your muscle type profile,
in maintaining your strength and force,
and more. The third takeaway, if you're
interested, I have a free beginners
training program that's included in the
physionic community. You're welcome to
use it if you don't know where to start.
And finally, if you are already in your
60s and 70s and even beyond, I mentioned
don't despair. And that's because it's
not too late. There's brilliant
discoveries in people just starting to
lift weights at an advanced age. I cover
them right here. I hope you found this
as fascinating as I did. Thanks for
tuning in. I'll catch you in the next
one.